Curriculum Vitae for Ronald R. McHaney, CSP

8924 E. Red Oak Dr. Spokane, WA 99217 Cell 503-313-1879

E-mail – <u>ronmchaney@gmail.com</u>

OUALIFICATIONS

Certified Safety Professional (#12482) with experience at corporate, division and facility levels in primary metals, fabricated metals, mining, industrial chemicals, refractory, automobile assembly, shipbuilding as well as retail and warehouse operations.

Expertise in occupational safety, industrial hygiene, security, fire protection, Workers' Compensation, environmental affairs and health services.

Highly developed skills and significant record of accomplishment in the management of risks to people and property.

EDUCATION

BS, Industrial Security, Michigan State University, 1964.

EMPLOYMENT

1998-Present

President, McHaney & Associates, Inc., Spokane, WA

Safety, health and loss prevention consulting for clients throughout North America, with the emphasis on working with clients to increase the value of the Health and Safety Program within the overall structure of the company. Although McHaney & Associates is capable of providing a wide range of loss control services, our major areas of specialization are employee training, safety program auditing, and expert witness services.

1997-1998

Corporate Senior Safety Consultant, Kaiser Aluminum

Provided safety consulting services for all facilities within the Kaiser organization (North America, Europe and Africa). Developed and conducted safety training workshops for field safety personnel and line managers. Was a permanent member of the Corporate Executive Safety Council and the Corporate Safety Audit Team. Developed Corporate Safety and Health Standards and corresponding Audit Criteria. Chaired the Aluminum Association's Special Task Force for Special Hazards Clothing. Co-authored the Kaiser Aluminum Safety and Health Leadership Process Matrix and its measurement system.

1994-1997

Safety & Health Manager, Primary Aluminum Business Unit, Kaiser Aluminum Provided safety and health staff services to the President, Primary Aluminum Business Unit and Smelter Managers in North America, Europe and Africa. Was appointed to the International Primary Aluminum Institute Safety Committee and served as Chairman of the Electrical Safety Sub-Committee.

1992-1994

Safety & Loss Prevention Consultant, FRP Business Unit, Kaiser Aluminum
Provided safety and loss prevention consulting services to the Flat Rolled Products
Business Unit

Curriculum Vitae for Ronald R. McHaney, CSP

1974-1992	Various safety and health management positions at Kaiser Aluminum facilities
1972-1974	Safety Director, White Pine Copper Company, Copper Range Inc.
1970-1972	Human Resources Manager, Erie Marine Division, Litton Industries
1968.1970	Sr. Industrial Relations Representative, Kaiser Refractories
1966-1968	Safety Engineer, Ford Motor Company

PUBLICATIONS

"The Search for Protective Clothing for Workers Exposed to the Hazards of Molten Aluminum and Molten Bath", (R. R. McHaney), <u>Health and Safety in Mining and Metallurgy</u>, 1996.

"It's Time to take a Stance on Compliance to Part 46", (R. R. McHaney and M. A. Copeland), <u>Aggregates Management Magazine</u>, 2000.

"Safety Solution: Conveyor Spillage Prevention", (Ron McHaney), NIOSH, 2002 http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/mining/topics/machinesafety/equipmentdsgn/conveyorspillage.htm,

"Safety Solution: Preventing Slide-Backs on Slope Conveyors", (Ron McHaney), NIOSH, 2002 http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/mining/topics/machinesafety/equipmentdsgn/slidebacks.htm

The state of the s

"The Advantage of Training for Value", (Ron McHaney), <u>Aggregates Manager</u>, October 2003.

"Beating the Hidden Costs of Safety Training", (Kristi McHaney and Ron McHaney), <u>Aggregates Manager</u>, November/December 2004.

"A Competitive Advantage – Searching for a Champion", (Kristi McHaney and Ron McHaney), Stone, Sand & Gravel Review, January/February 2005.

Patty's Industrial Hygiene, Sixth Edition, Volume 4, Part VIII; Specialty Areas of Practice, Chapter 47; Emergency and Disaster: Preparedness, Response and Recovery, 2011, (Ron McHaney), Section 1.4 "Planned and Unplanned Events"; Section 7.1 "Natural Threats"; Section 7.5 "Civil Unrest, Workplace Violence & Strikes".

PAPER PRESENTATIONS

"A System for Sharing Solutions", (R.R. McHaney, Steve Anderson) paper presented at the 1995 Meeting of the International Primary Aluminum Institute Safety Committee, Paris, France.

"The Search for Protective Clothing for Workers Exposed to the Hazards of Molten Aluminum and Molten Bath", (R. R. McHaney) paper presented at the 1996 Institution of Mining and Metallurgy International Conference on Health and Safety In Mining and Metallurgy, Regent's College, London, England.

"Safety Solutions Network", (R.R. McHaney) paper presented at the 1996 Aluminum Industry Loss Prevention Workshop, Orlando Florida.

"Training for Value", (R. R. McHaney and M. A. Copeland), paper presented at the California Mining Association Conference, Sacramento, California, February 13 - 15, 2001.

Curriculum Vitae for Ronald R. McHaney, CSP

"Safety Compliance – Are You Really Prepared (R. R. McHaney) paper presented at the California Precast Concrete Association Conference, Las Vegas, Nevada, November 10, 2006.

PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

- American Society of Safety Professionals
- Board of Certified Safety Professionals
- ANSI Z117.1 Committee Safety Requirements for Confined Spaces